Hello everyone and welcome
to EnglishPod, my name is Marko.
My name is Catherine and
today we're talking about fear.
That's right, today
we're going to talk about
phobias, different types
of fears that you have.
Many people have,
many people are scared of
different things and that's what
we're going to talk about today.
Okay, so let's listen
to today's dialogue
and find out what the people in
our dialogue are very, very afraid of.
Are you excited about your trip next month?
Yes, and no.
I can't wait to go to Europe
but at the same time I'm terrified.
Why?
Well, I have aerofobia, I
have a chronic fear of flying.
Oh really?
I have an uncle who is
also terrified of flying.
It's not that bad
though, I mean it is pretty
scary to be up in this big machine flying
through the air, it's 700 miles per hour.
I actually have arachnophobia.
You're scared of spiders?
I actually have two more phobias,
acrophobia and glossophobia.
I guess that explains why you're afraid of
flying but public speaking is not that bad.
Are you kidding?
When I get on stage
my palms start to
sweat, I get really nervous
and I can hardly speak.
Well, I must confess that
I am a bit claustrophobic.
I hate being in an elevator
for more than five seconds.
We are such weirdos, right?
All right, we're back so let's take a look
at those phobias on language takeaway.
Language takeaway.
The first phobia that we
have is called aerofobia.
That's right, aerofobia and that
means that you are scared of flying.
Okay, so we can tell
because phobia means a
fear of something,
but it's not just a fear.
It means that if you go
on an airplane you get very,
very upset, you think
that you're going to die.
That's right.
So phobia is a very
serious fear, but
aeroplane is the prefix, so aerofobia
is a fear of going on airplanes.
That's right.
Another phobia that we
have is arachnophobia.
So again, as you see in the prefix,
arachnophobia is related to a spider.
That's right.
So this comes from the origins of English.
I'm not sure if it's
Greek or Latin, but
arachnophobia like arachnid
has to do with spiders.
So I'm afraid of spiders
if I have arachnophobia.
That is right.
And now taking a look
at two more types of
phobias here, we have
acrophobia and glossophobia.
So let's take a look at
the first one, acrophobia.
So acrophobia, acro has to do with heights.
So I don't like to be on tall buildings.
I don't like to maybe
look down from heights.
That means I'm afraid of heights.
That's right.
You're afraid of being at a
very high altitude, acrophobia.
Now glossophobia, it's
an interesting one because
this one you are scared
of public speaking
or you get very nervous when
you're in front of a group of people.
So this is actually a
very, very common fear.
But if it's a serious fear, it's a phobia.
So glossophobia means
that when you go in front
of people, you get
very, very anxious, upset.
Your stomach hurts.
You have wet hands.
So that's a very serious fear.
That's right.
And for our last phobia,
we have cholesterol phobia.
I think is one of the most common ones.
If you have cholesterol phobia,
you're afraid of smaller tight spaces.
That's right.
So people who, so you heard
the word "closter phobic."
Or people who are claustrophobic, or people
who suffer from claustrophobia, don't like
to be in small, tight places like
elevators, for example, tunnels.
So now you brought up an interesting point.
Our last phobia, we said claustrophobic.
And now we must make
the difference between, for
example, claustrophobia
and being claustrophobic.
So a phobia, you hear
the word, I hear the ending,
I-A-Cphobia, claustrophobia
is a noun, okay?
That means I can talk about,
I have it, I have this fear.
But when you're talking
about the adjective,
something that describes you, you
would have to use the ick ending.
I'm claustrophobic.
He is acrophobic.
They are aerofobic.
Okay.
So that is the adjective form.
So if I say, I have
arachnophobia, it means I
have this fear, or I can
say, I am arachnophobic.
Great.
So this can be used for
all other kinds of phobias.
So when you learn those words,
remember that there's two different kinds.
There's the I-A, phobia, which is the
noun, and ick, which is the adjective.
All right.
Let's listen to our dialogue again, and
we'll be back in a bit with fluency builder.
Are you excited about your trip next month?
Yes, and no.
I can't wait to go to Europe,
but at the same time, I'm terrified.
Why?
Well, I have arachnophobia.
I have a chronic fear of flying.
Oh, really?
I have an uncle who is
also terrified of flying.
It's not that bad, though.
I mean, it is pretty scary to be up in
this big machine flying through the air.
Oh, 700 miles per hour.
I actually have arachnophobia.
You're scared of spiders.
I actually have two more phobias.
Acrophobia and glossophobia.
I guess that explains
why you're afraid of
flying, but public
speaking is not that bad.
Are you kidding?
When I get on stage,
my palms start to sweat.
I get really nervous,
and I can hardly speak.
Well, I must confess that
I am a bit claustrophobic.
I hate being in an elevator
for more than five seconds.
We are such weirdos, right?
All right.
So we've picked out a couple
of different phrases today.
Let's take a look at those
now on fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
So in the beginning
of today's dialogue, the
character said, I cannot wait to go to
Europe, but at the same time, I'm terrified.
So at the same time.
So in this case, we're saying that
we are happy, but also we are scared.
So two things at once, at the same time.
Right.
So this is a little bit
different from when we
talk about, I can do two
things at the same time.
I can walk and chew gum.
More talking about feelings or emotions.
You say, I'm happy, but at
the same time, I'm also scared.
That means that I have these two feelings,
and actually they're opposite feelings.
Right.
Usually, they are opposite feelings.
So like you say, you're happy, but
at the same time, you're nervous.
It's like saying, on the other hand.
Exactly.
All right.
Now, when we talked
about all these fears, we're
afraid of flying, we are afraid of spiders,
we describe them as a chronic fear.
Okay.
So this adjective chronic is very
important because it has to do with time.
Okay.
So I have a chronic fear of heights.
That means this is a
fear I've always had, okay?
And I will always have.
You can also say, she
has chronic back pain.
Okay.
That means it comes back again and again.
It's not just one time,
it's all, it's some person's
whole life, maybe, not
every day, but it comes back.
Right.
Okay.
So that's, if you say you have a chronic
something you're explaining that you've had
it for a while or you will always have
it, something usually very serious also.
And going back to one of the
phobias, we mentioned galasso phobia.
And the other person said, well, you
know, public speaking is not that bad.
It's not, it's not something
to be so afraid of.
And the other person replied
by saying, are you kidding?
Are you kidding?
So this is actually a way of
showing some sarcasm when
you're talking because
public speaking is not that bad.
The person wants to
say, no, it is that bad.
Right.
It is awful.
You're kidding is a way
to say, no, I totally disagree.
Right.
So you're being a
little bit sarcastic, but at
the same time, you're
also acting a bit surprised.
Like, I can't believe
you said that or like, if
I said, I really like the
Twilight movies, Marco.
Are you kidding?
Those movies are terrible.
All right.
So Marco does not agree with my opinion.
Now, when we're talking about public
speaking, we mentioned that you get on stage.
So this is very important because this
is the action to get on stage and speak.
Okay.
So if you have a stage
or maybe even you
don't have a stage,
but you're talking about
performing in front of other people, like a
speech or a play, you say you get on stage.
And it's important to
remember this as a phrase.
Right.
So whenever I get on
stage, I start to sweat.
Now, you may want to
add the, there you want
to say to get on the
stage, but it's not necessary.
Not incorrect, but
the usual or let's say
more correct form would just
be use the phrase to get on stage.
When I get on stage, I get very nervous.
You don't have to say
when I get on the stage
or she's normally
very shy, but when she
gets on stage, she opens up
and becomes very, very talkative.
That's right.
All right.
So that's all the phrases
we've picked out for you.
Let's listen to our dialogue one
last time and we'll be right back.
Are you excited about your trip next month?
Yes.
And no, I can't wait to go to Europe,
but at the same time, I'm terrified.
Why?
Well, I have aerofobia.
I have a chronic fear of flying.
Oh, really?
I have an uncle who is
also terrified of flying.
It's not that bad, though.
I mean, it is pretty scary to be up in
this big machine flying through the air.
It's 700 miles per hour.
I actually have arachnophobia.
You're scared of spiders.
I actually have two more phobias,
acrophobia and glossophobia.
I guess that explains
why you're afraid of
flying, but public
speaking is not that bad.
Are you kidding?
When I get on stage,
my palms start to sweat.
I get really nervous
and I can hardly speak.
Well, I must confess that
I am a bit claustrophobic.
I hate being in an elevator
for more than five seconds.
We are such weirdos, right?
All right, so talking
about all these phobias,
now one of these
phobias was actually made
into a movie, I think, in 1990, arachnophobia,
this very chronic fear of spiders.
That's right.
And so I remember when
I was younger and this
movie came out, everybody started
talking about how they were arachnophobic.
They had this horrible fear of spiders.
Did you ever see that movie?
Yeah, of course, of course.
It's terrifying.
Yes, it was supposedly
some South American
spider that made its way into the United
States on a box in a crate or something.
Now, many people
handle phobias differently.
Now, do you have any phobia, are you
claustrophobic, are you arachnophobic?
I don't have any phobias and I'm not really
afraid of anything, so I'm pretty lucky
that way, but I know a
number of people who are afraid
of heights, acrophobic,
and so that's pretty common.
And actually, if you
look it up, you will
find in dictionary, maybe
hundreds of phobias,
people who are afraid
of open spaces, people
who are afraid of close spaces, or people
who are afraid of marriage, they even have
a phobia determined
for this type of person.
So it's very interesting.
Now, this is going to be a challenge.
Why don't you look
up a couple of different
phobias and share with
us, maybe some of the
craziest ones, or the funniest ones, or
maybe the strangest ones you can find?
That's right.
So, look them up, share them with us.
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
All right.
We'll see you guys there.
Bye.